A Guide to the Marcus Morton Hawes Civil War Letters 1861-1862
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Marcus Morton Hawes Civil War Letters 1861-1862
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11372
This collection consists of twenty-one Civil War letters
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These letters were purchased by the University of Virginia Library from Butterfield & Butterfield, Book Auction Galleries, San Francisco, California, on August 8, 1997.
Biographical/Historical Information
Marcus Morton Hawes, son of William and Maria (daughter of Governor Marcus Morton) Hawes, was born in New Bedford, Massachusetts, but moved to Boston in 1844, attending the Boston Latin School and a school run by Epes S. Dixwell, and graduating from Harvard in 1858. He was in the commission business until the war, and became a first lieutenant on May 24, 1861. On August 12, 1861, he was appointed acting- quartermaster, and became actual quartermaster on November 27. On the 31st of March, 1862, he was acting brigade-commissary, and was appointed assistant-quartermaster, with the rank of captain on July 17, 1862. He remained with General George Henry Gordon until November 1862, when he was assigned to duty with General Andrews, about to go south in the expedition of General Nathaniel Prentiss Banks, in command of the Gulf in the Red River Campaign of 1863.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of twenty-one Civil War letters of Lt. Morton Hawes (1836-?), Quartermaster, 2nd Regiment, [Infantry], Massachusetts Volunteers, from various camps in Virginia and Maryland, to his mother, Maria Morton Hawes, and each letter has a typed transcript. The 2nd Regiment was organized at Camp Andrew, West Roxbury, Massachusetts, and mustered in May 25, 1861. The letters tell about battles, camp life, speculation about the outcome of the War, comments on both the Union and the Confederate soldiers' fighting ability and strengths. Accompanying the letters are two photographs, including an original albumen photograph of Hawes and a photograph of an oil painting of his grandmother, Mary Hawes (1769-1859).
Contents List
- Letter [1861] Sunday (Box 1)
  Morton, New York, mentions a walk to the Metropolitan, a talk with Dr. P[?], and plans to leave for Washington that day.
- Letter [1861 May] Friday (Box 1)
  Morton, Andover, Massachusetts, has received his appointment as a 1st Lt. in the U.S. Army; his company is in camp at Fort Warren, Major Gordon's Regiment, with his address in care of Captain Underwood, Camp Andrews, headquarters Gordon Regiment.
- Letter [1861 Jul 11] Thursday (Box 1)
  Morton, Hagerstown, Maryland, felt the heat very much in B[altimore?] on Monday, his regiment marching to join General Patterson about twenty miles away; General Joseph Johnston is retiring toward "the Gap" and Richmond, Virginia, and there will be no fighting yet; about Hagerstown, he writes, "This town is about half and half but the secessionists dare not say a word, they were drawn out some ten days ago & now the town is under martial law by a Connecticut Regiment the 4th."
- Letter [1861 Jul 14?] Sunday (Box 1)
  Morton, Martinsburg, Virginia, arrived Friday evening after a march of twenty miles, waded the Potomac on foot, enemy camp fires within sight, 33,000 federal troops in town, believes they are underestimating the enemy, "I have no idea it is going to be a straight march to victory," the rebels destroyed some forty locomotives, the railroad, bridges, and private property in Martinsburg before they were driven out, but they are very strong in Winchester.
- Letter [1861 Jul 21?] Sunday (Box 1)
  Morton, Monocacy, Maryland, on Monday after his last letter written from Martinsburg, his regiment started on a long march and reached a small place called Bunker Hill, scattering a company of cavalry in town, and stayed until Wednesday, when they marched 35,000 men strong to Charles Town, a distance of twelve miles, his position was in the extreme rear guarding the rear battery, a part of Governor Sprague's artillery he brought to Washington; his regiment chosen to march to Harpers Ferry and occupy the town and open communications; the regiment is now located on the grounds occupied formerly by the Superintendent of the U.S. Arsenal, the destruction of property widespread, on Saturday, his company was detailed to guard the aqueduct, a large stone work on the canal, where they seized a large lot of medicines, clothing, and arms concealed in the woods to be sent to the Army of Virginia.
- Letter [1861] Aug 4 Sunday (Box 1)
  Morton, constantly on the move, without conveniences, tents, paper or ink, sleeping on the ground, with his division on the Maryland side of the Potomac River, except for three companies of his regiment occupying Harpers Ferry, asks for his family's help in securing an appointment as 1st Lt. in the Regular Army from Washington, Colonel George Henry Gordon may be leaving in a few days with his appointment as Brigadier General.
- Letter [1861 Aug 14?] (Box 1)
  Morton, Maryland Heights, living in the woods with no shelter & much rain, two days ago appointed on Colonel Gordon's staff as quartermaster to the regiment, describes his duties, and gives his assessment of the conflict, "I now predict that they will soon make a move which will take us all aback, or at any rate we shall not at present gain any material advantage. The North will find out that they are fighting with equals, the Artillery is met with guns twice in no. & efficiency - & mere drabbling politicians are out-generalled by the height of Military talent - [Winfield?] Scott has got against him nearly all the Gens. By whom he has formerly gained his victories."
- Letter [1861 Aug] 25 Sunday (Box 1)
  Morton, Hyattsville, Maryland, new duties as quartermaster keeping him busy, thankful for the advice of Lt. Colonel Andrews about his desire to seek an position as officer in the regular army, refers to the First Battle of Bull Run, his pay is now $154.50 per month, with two horses, three servants, and clerks, has engaged Jack Denmark, a regular Virginia servant, as his barber, cook, boot black, ironer, and washer, mentions their skirmish at Harpers Ferry, where their Enfield rifles carried beautifully, most of the regiment's marching has been alone and through a country entirely hostile, and asks her to direct letters care of General Banks Division, Maryland.
- Letter [1861] Sep 3 (Box 1)
  Morton, Camp near Darnstown, part of his duties include making preparations for transportation which allows him advance notice of troop movements, believes his regiment will soon move towards Washington, D.C. and then into Virginia, refers to rumors about the death of [Jefferson?] Davis, has taken a very fine horse away from a secessionist, voices some criticism of General Nathaniel Prentiss Banks.
- Letter [1861?] Sep 25 (Box 1)
  Morton, Washington, has been on the road most of the time to Philadelphia and Washington, on business for Colonel Gordon, will try to join Gordon's staff when he becomes general, and sends some materials he captured while crossing the river into Virginia [incomplete].
- Letter [1861] Nov 17 Sunday (Box 1)
  Morton, has been sick and suffering from the winter weather, must soon go into winter quarters, attempts being made to transfer the regiment to the Naval Expedition but tied up in red tape for the present, Colonel Gordon is in Boston until Thanksgiving, and urges his family to use its influence to get him into the regular army.
- Letter [1861?] Dec 5 (Box 1)
  Morton, Frederick, Maryland, arrived today after a hard and cold march, no time to forward a letter by Captain Underwood, and has received their letter regarding Colonel Gordon.
- Letter [1862] Feb 24 Monday (Box 1)
  Morton, Camp, will move within an hour upon Harpers Ferry, through Virginia, to Winchester, and expects a grand movement very soon.
- Letter 1862 Jun 16 (Box 1)
  Morton, Front Royal, Virginia, apologizes for his silence since the battle and retreat [Battle of Winchester?], has sent the deed signed in Baltimore to them, Colonel Gordon has finally got his promotion to general and appointed him to his staff, hopefully as captain and assistant quartermaster, believes General George McClellan will be defeated at Richmond, P.G.T. Beauregard is there with a large force from Corinth, Mississippi, the Union will have to resort to conscription to have enough men, and describes the retreat through the streets of Winchester, Virginia, "Women firing from the windows and it was pretty hard, it was a dire necessity but a true one to shoot them in their windows as they killed our wearied and defeated men dragging their bodies and equipments through heat and dust. Still on our return the imbecile doubly careful (?) politician Banks allowed no just retribution to be taken. The City still stands a monument of Southern cruelty & Northern weakness a refuge for other bloody deeds which may happen any day."
- Letter 1862 Jul 15 (Box 1)
  Morton, Warrenton, Virginia, have been to Washington on business and now cut off from his regiment by swollen streams, waiting in a little dirty hotel to join them, criticizes the North for its sleepy inactivity in the face of a foe, with more men more skillfully managed, better attitude, and fighting at home, wishes the army would impose "a military dictator & put down this rebellion through one head & one mind I would enforce this upon Lincoln Stanton & Co. by the bayonets" and believes the South has adopted a more enlightened plan of leadership.
- Letter 1862 Aug 2 (Box 1)
  Morton, Camp near Washington, in Virginia, writes, "we are now under the great Pope & we have already made up our minds he is more than half humbug," leave canceled for the present, drafting for the North has been instituted, strongly criticizes the actions of the Governor of Massachusetts, does not believe in "people rule," Captain Underwood has gotten a position as Lt. Colonel in one of the new regiments, the 33rd, which is led by Colonel Albert C. Maggi, who kept a gymnasium in N.B. and was involved in a scandal with Mrs. Charles Howland.
- Letter 1862 Aug 26 (Box 1)
  Morton, Bull Run, writes, "I wrote you just after our terrific slaughter at Cedar Mountain Now the whole Richmond Army is on us & we have retreated, the wagons are here and the troops about 20 miles beyond. We have abandoned per force, nearly all our acquirements of the past year. Here I am right near the old battlefield. McClellan is with us, but the enemy can get through the valley, destroy the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, and go into Maryland."
- Letter 1862 Sep 5 (Box 1)
  Morton, near Washington, describes the events of the last few weeks, at the Battle of Second Bull Run "Everything has been so confused and so disastrous that we have had neither mail or in many cases food. The people do not know it but we have had a series of unparalleled defeats without the least ray of the sunshine of victory." He severely criticizes President Lincoln, General John Pope, and the United States government, points out that the South is fighting for their homes and families, while many Northerners are fighting for abstractions, such as the flag, believes the Rebels can take Washington and Maryland, and mentions his regiment has been driven out of Virginia three times.
- Letter 1862 Sep 16 (Box 1)
  Morton, Frederick, Maryland, has just experienced the Battle of Antietam with tremendous loss on both sides, General Reno was shot and killed in the battle, Morton's extreme dislike of General Pope.
- Letter Monday evening (Box 1)
  Morton, Camp, forgot her bundle, but made up a large bundle to send Woolard, heard preaching from James Freeman Clarke to all the regiments, describes the tent arrangement, officers are made up of the highest toned gentlemen of Boston, mentions Harry Russell, Tom Robeson, and two sons of Judge Abbot of Lowell.
- Letter n.d. (Box 1)
  Morton, [Frederick, Maryland], men are going into winter quarters, with drawings of the shed he occupies, [letter missing beginning page(s)].